I'm going to walk you through how to
detox your home so we're working on
detoxing our system but we want to work
on detox in our home our environment
because where you spend most of your
time that could also be a large
contributor of exposures so let's get
into
it from today's presentation I hope that
you all um are able to to learn
effective strategies for reducing your
toxic exposure in your home from food
packaging storage cookware air care
products there's so much I can talk
about but I chose to get just talk about
the high level things okay the ones that
most people that can be you know a
source of tox toxins in our homes most
people use a lot of plastic so plastic
is everywhere our food packaging storage
containers the the f um eating utensils
we're exposed to plastic it's it's
ubiquitous and plastic is is a a
cocktail of different thades BPA methyl
Mercury DDT styrenes BCBS the list goes
on it's there's a lot that we're exposed
to and this is interesting the
University of norstrom found that food
packaging is high in levels pasas and P
are a class of there's over 12,000
different chemicals in this class and
they have known effects on uh impacts on
health negative impacts and they're
known as forever chemicals they're
forever chemicals because they don't
break down and that's what makes them
dangerous they actually can concentrate
in the liver and the kidneys and create
problems
this was the this is data from the CDC
their from their biomonitoring studies
the CDC conducts biomonitoring studies
to to get an idea of how much chemicals
or different things that the public is
exposed to and what they found was that
past chemicals could be detected in
Blood of 98% of the US population so
these chemicals are ubiquitous like BPA
they're and they're some people can have
can have high amount of these in in
their blood and you can actually see it
and somewhat correlate with their
condition their health condition so what
you see here let me minimize
this this is the P structure so p is a
pneumonic for poly or per florals this
molecule past chemicals have a lot of
Floral fide atoms okay so you could see
all the
Florine and when we get exposed to it
either from food packaging as the study
from the University of nadam found we
have it in cookwar in contaminated food
the food is contaminated because the
packaging is what carries it once it's
in the system it can impact the our
lipid chemistry of impact in our
cholesterol and because is a hormone end
endocrine disrupting chemical it can
lead to
obesity and lead to weight gain it it
affects our metabolism and and how we've
metabolized lipids and glucose and so
that can increase the risk for met
metabolic syndrome or a type two
diabetes as I mention is stores in the
liver so it can be a hepatic toxin or
hepatic toxic to to the liver cells and
promote liver conditions preclampsia so
here's the thing past
chemicals again because of the endocrine
disrupting effects that it has just
virtually every endocrine system in a
body it can lead to infertility it's
been shown to be quite elevated in women
with
PCOS uh it because it affects it's a
because it it's a hormone disruptor it
affects steroid sex hormones which means
that it will affect reproductive health
and uh cause fertility or lead to low
low birth weight um in a fetus or a baby
that's born and miscarriage and
preclampsia the list goes on neurod
degeneration because of the impact it
creates in the the nervous system it
causes low grade neural inflammation it
also disrupts the immune system and te-
cell
differentiation lower antibody
production when you disrupt the immune
system if it causes some kind of change
or alterations to how your immune system
works that can increase the risk for
cancer because your immune system is
your military for getting rid of
abnormal cells that are uh growing so
lower immunity increase risk for cancer
and organ toxicity as kind of what I
talked about with the liver this is why
we don't want past in our food packaging
our storage containers because of the
multi-stem effect that that it has on
our
body this is the thyroid so the thyroid
is an endocrine structure as well
and when we're exposed to past and C the
blood can again I mentioned it immune
disregulation so it it can affect our
thyroid antibodies can Elevate them it
can ALS which impacts the thyroid it can
cause abnormal thyroid function
something else the reason why I showed
the fluoride structure of what a past
chemical looks like is because the th
thyroid is a tissue that uptakes iodine
iodine is really important for the
synthesis of T4 T3 hormone and and when
we don't have adequate iodine that can
disrupt the T4 T3
production past chemicals can disrupt
thyroid function because the
fluoride and it it's this this
phenomenon call it's an antagonism
fluoride thyroid iodine antagonism so
the fluoride atom is a lower atomic
weight than iodine so it
displaces iodine in a thyroid and it
causes obviously thyroid dysfunction so
one of the important things when we
consider thyroid health and Hyper or
hypo thyroidism we should really get an
assess of a patient's environmental
exposures to past chemicals because they
the fluoride can displace iodine and
affect how the thyroid
works and of course there's some
Downstream consequences to a thyroid
that's not working properly affects the
the brain and and so this is too
something I I also want to mention is a
an example of functional medicine
because we look at systems biology is
what we do if there's something wrong
with a system we need to look at how the
individual systems are interacting with
one another and how the environment how
our bodies are interacting with the
environment and so you could see past
exposure is causing immune disregulation
which affects thyroid
function but there's also that direct
interaction of past chemicals and
displace an iodine in a thyroid and
effect in thyroid production hormone
production and then there's Downstream
effects of that on the brain everything
is all interconnected and we have to
think like that whenever there's
anything going
on so this is what happens when you're
not carefully and properly using plastic
so dishw when you're putting your
plastic in a dishwasher or using hot
water
that can damage the plastic plastic
breaks down never do that it's not good
you um putting acidic Foods Citrus Foods
Tomatoes anything like that in plastic
it can actually accelerate the breakdown
of
plastic
microwave when you place plastic in a
microwave it breaks down okay and if
you're using scrub brushes that are
harsh that's going to help that's going
to create scratches on the plastic and
it's going to create opportunity for
things to come off the plastic okay so
you have to use have take proper care in
how you use plastic or just avoid it
okay so this was looking at microplastic
scientists were looking at microplastics
coming from food containers and this is
an animal study but we use animal models
to get an idea of what can happen in
humans So eventually and I think we even
already have some animal study or human
studies on the effects of
microplastics in humans food containers
what they found was food containers
exposed to high temperatures released
more than 10 million microplastics per
milliliter in water microplastics are
the other reasons why you would avoid
plastic cookware or storage
containers the pl microplastics are
these tiny plastic particles that you
can inhale you can get them um through
your food source and they have Delirious
effects on health from an oxidative uh
stress perspective more oxidative stress
promotes tissue damage
neurotoxins promotes neurotoxicity
reproductive toxicity
these are they're known to facilitate
cancer development and alter metabolism
so microplastics are really bad now what
do they look like oh let me at least say
this so when you're trying to reduce
your plastic
exposure this is what you want to swap
to so here you have plastic on the left
you want to swap to Glass and you can
use glass mason jars or storage
containers
glass whet or stainless steel or yeah
stainless steel or glass water bottles
okay so this is plastic cooking utensils
you want to replace those cooking
utensils with wood or stainless steel
bamboo so these are some alternatives to
plastic cooking
utensils Ramen imagin is a company that
did a test on the number of particles
that come from a scratch of Teflon so
Teflon is
non-stick material that contains past
chemicals as well and what they found
was that there were 9,000 plastic
particles released from one scratch of
Teflon and as many as 2.3 million tiny
particles during meal prep within 30
seconds so there's a lot of plastic
particles coming off the uh Teflon and
Air
fryers uh non-stick air fryers are made
from Teflon so when you're using the air
fryer or anything nonstick it will
create these release these plastic
particles that we don't want and P fast
chemicals we don't want if you're um
interested in using an air fryer you do
use it but not very
often I mean just one use is quite
damaging if it's a non-stick one so they
have a glass air fryer I did create in
the membership a document of other types
of air fryers that are not glass but
they're not as toxic yeah I have that
and that should be
available okay so reducing chemical
exposure when you're using an air fryer
try to avoid non stick coating or
plastic if you can I apologize for the
formatting
here uh look for shiny gray interior
that's the a rule of thumb if you're not
sure what Teflon looks like it normally
has this shiny gray black appearance and
that's if you're looking for any cookwar
that looks like that's something you
want to avoid because it has past
chemicals and it's not going to be um
healthy to use look for stainless steel
or ceramic or glass if you can and use
this is
another Nuance to using air fryers or
just cooking in your your home use
proper ventilation and use the air fryer
over a stove top and use stove fan you
have to use the stove fan it's there for
a reason and this is something else when
you're cooking in your home use a HEPA
filter
it's important because your indoor air
quality is actually more toxic than
outdoor okay so he a filter every time
you're using an air fryer every time
you're cooking because you're inhaling
all of those those those chemicals and
if people are frying you're in oil
you're also getting more chemicals or if
you're burning stuff more chemicals if
if you absolutely have to use plastic
avoid Heating in plastic use plastic
only for storing cold
items and get in a habit of looking at
the resin or looking for the resin
identification code so every plastic
that you use has a Cod at the
bottom um it's a tiny triangle at the
bottom and that number indicates what
the plastic is made of and in general
even if you don't know what the number
designation is at least remember that
numbers one two four and five are BP
free okay that's just something to note
and if if you ever in a situation where
you're in a pinch you have to use some
plastic and you just you know sometimes
you can't avoid it like the five five
gallon water um containers they're
actually made from either one two three
or four some are not just get in a habit
of reading looking at your plastic and
identifying the resin identification
code how many of you use plastic cutting
boards so the University of North Dakota
found uh when you're cut in on plastic
and they actually used carrots in this
study
but the fascinating part of this is
when they cut on a plastic chopping
board they found there was 15 milligrams
of microplastics per
cut or about 50 gram per year which is
the equivalent if you want to put it in
perspective 10 plastic credit
cards 10 plastic credit cards of
and and that's per cut that's really
alarming this here the cutting board if
you look to the right you see the
plastic that is those are microplastics
and that is what goes in your food so
when you use a plastic cutting board for
every cut I mean just imagine how much
you're you're slicing on it right you're
for every cut you're creating these tiny
minute plastic particles that are in
your food and a lot of times you can't
see them because they're so small and
the food is
actually covering the microplastic so
you can't see it that's a problem what
you want to do is swap out your plastic
cutting boards for wood there's two
benefits to that of course you're not
getting the exposure to the
microplastics but you're also wood is
antibacterial so bacteria does not
survive on wood and surfaces because the
the way the wood behaves it traps the
bacteria and they die for that reason
for a hygiene reason that's why you
would use
wood how many of you consume brown rice
a or sorry do you consume brown rice a
no I don't like it B yes I prefer brown
rice over white rice and C
sometimes what's your answers Consumer
Reports found that brown rice has 80%
more inorganic arsenic on average in
white rice and the reason being because
the Arsenic accumulates in the grain's
outer layers which is removed from white
rice which is why brown rice is more
healthier than white rice rice but
there's some there's some negatives to
that as well because of the Arsenic and
so what you want to do when you're
sourcing rice is to the brown that's MTI
rice from California India Pakistan is
the best choice and they they tested the
rice and there's not these rice even
though they're is arsenic they have a
lower concentration of Arsenic and I
also want to make mention that if your
rice does not come from if you're in the
US and your rice does not come from
California or India Pakistan or if it
comes from places like Missouri or Texas
or Louisiana these places or Michigan
they have tested high for arsenic
compared to
California
okay now other grains have arsenic but
quinoa
buckwhat and Millet have lower amounts
of of
arsonate so when you're looking for
healthy rice or good rice that's low in
Arsenic you want to Source from the the
places I indicated you also want to wash
until you can um wash until it's clear
to reduce the Arsenic levels when you're
washing it you're rinsing it and it's
kind of foamy looking keep cleaning it
until it's clear that reduces arsenic by
30% you also use what is called the
pasta method which reduces it
60% and what that is is you're
increasing like you would cook pasta you
you have a higher ratio of water to a
smaller ratio of rice so six to 10 cups
water one cup rice and you discard the
ex you're not going to cook that so the
traditional way that people cook
rice or con um conventional way is to
cook the water uh cook the rice until
the water is gone but no with this
method you're actually cooking the rice
and you test it and see if it's soft and
then you drain it and that's actually
what's used in um places like India and
Pakistan that's how they cook their rice
whether they I don't know if they're
knowing that there that's actually
reducing arsenic levels when they cook
like that but it happens that's a
protective way of
reducing your arsenic
levels so what this slide is just
there's some other stuff regarding the
kitchen that we can really behavioral
things lifestyle practices that we can
consider when we're we're trying to
reduce our toxin exposure in the kitchen
you want to avoid cam products due to
BPA exposure they line cans with BPA I
can go that's a whole another this like
I said can be there's a lot of content
to and stuff to talk about but I really
don't have enough time so I had to just
condense it here but BPA is it the
company's manufacturers ly cans with BPA
to prevent
corrosion and obviously BPA an impact on
health and endocrine system we don't
want BPA we want to expose our our I
mean reduce our exposure to bisphenols
tetrax is material as
primarily primarily paper so you'll see
some contain some foods packaged in that
kind of material and then if you're
looking for BPA can BPA free cans eating
Foods is a company and there's starting
to be other companies that are somewhat
going in this Direction with creating
BPA free product or storage containers
or cans so eating Foods is one company
and I'm sure there's more uh that you
can find but I know that there this
company is extremely
transparent and we'll talk about that
too but you want to be able if you're
not sure about something you need to be
able to call the company and ask them
questions that need to be transparent
and some companies are not transparent
Eden Foods is BPA create BPA free cans
okay and I can't speak to bisphenols
because remember I said there's a class
of B fenals and BPA is just one of them
there's many others BPS and P bpb you
know there's a whole lot of them and so
I think eaten Foods is one that has
absolutely no bisphenols but the other
companies I don't know but they do have
BPA free you have to look for
them avoid microwave popcorn how many
eat microwave popcorn so from the
saturated fat part you know obviously
you don't eat it for that reason but the
paper that's used so there's two there's
two chemicals that are in microwavable
popcorn so there's dietal which is what
makes it
buttery and then there's the past
chemicals on the lining if you look at
the plastic or you look at the inside of
a the popcorn bag you can see this resin
like material on the interior
of and that is that's peast that's the
past chemical that I was telling you
that you need to avoid so you don't
consume microwave popcorn avoid glazed
and unglazed clay cookware there's a you
know I can present a case on that that's
a whole another thing but basically lead
is the concern there and store
condiments in glass if possible if you
can if you like condiments try to get
them in
glass and but remember genetics lows a
gun environment pulls a trigger
lifestyle pulls a trigger
you do the best you can and you're not
going to be able to totally eliminate
everything but things that you have
control over you do that avoid
scratching scrubbing plastic appliances
when you're or putting hot or acidic
Foods in them so you know how you're
using your blender or you're using a
food processor try to avoid scratching
and scrubbing okay try to avoid using
hot water uh don't put them in a
dishwasher nothing like that try not to
use hot water when you're cleaning these
plastic containers okay and you can
consider a stainless steel immersion
blender for hot soups and
beverages so this um was a a small study
that looked at the impact of just going
3 days without plastic or cans and uh
they were measuring urinary
metabolites of BPA and phalates and what
they found was that just three days of
avoiding is BPA concentrations dropped
by
66% and phalate metabolite the DEA dehp
metabolite a phalate phalate chemical
dropped by between 53 and
56% so this is amazing just making
better choices of you know what you're
using can really dramatically drop these
concentrations of you reduce your
exposure being more conscious about what
you're using in your
home so going to the living room do you
currently use scented wall fragrance or
candles I remember one of the things I'm
I have such a it's a pet peeve of
m i I go to an Airbnb and there's just
so much fragrance I don't like it it's
way too many chemicals and it's so bad
because the chemicals are mainly I'm
going to talk about them but they have
Benzene Benzene is a heavy molecule and
you when you leave out the house and you
get in your car and you can still smell
the fragrance almost as if you sprayed
yourself with perfume and you just
walked into a place
okay that is bad it shouldn't be like
that
okay okay so the University of
Massachusetts they say here that air
fresheners can impact indoor air quality
by adding to potentially hazardous
pollutants to the air and the use of air
fresheners is associated with elevated
levels of volatile organic compounds
VC's and the VC's are from Malahide
aceto alide Benzene
tuline list goes on and there's over
were I mean there's so many of these
chemicals a hundred different types of
blcs and I recall when I was in medical
school I had colleagues who when were
conducting autopsy we didn't conduct
autopsies in medical school but the
kadaver so we had to be in a a kadaver
lab working on for gross anatomy and my
colleagues could not handle the falah
heide it was was so bad they were
breaking out in rashes and um having
respiratory symptoms just all kinds of
skin issues it was a horrible thing so
it it's a big problem when you're
exposed to that and some people are more
sensitive than others so this is what
the the different types of VCS that are
released from air fresheners but there
are other sources too so benzene's been
connected to neur the neurological
system respiratory system impacting
these various systems reproductive Chia
so
hematological uh blood cancers tuling
respiratory kidney liver I mean these
chemicals are impacting various organ
systems and VC's are up to 10 times
higher
indoors okay that's really bad because
you're exposed to this every
day so to consumer product safety
commission says a candle move it on from
air fresheners a candle with Lead Core
wig releases five times the amount of
lead considered hazardous for children
and exceeds EPA pollution standards for
outdoor air so your candles so you have
air fresheners that are releasing vlc's
and you have candles that are releasing
lead so incense
this was looking at inant smoke and the
impact on airway disease and what they
found is that on average incense burning
produces particulates greater than 45
milligrams per gram burned as compared
to 10 milligrams per gram burned for
cigarettes and what that basically is is
four times four and a half times more
particulates are created using an
incense compared to a cigarette
that's really
bad so you don't want to use incense you
don't want to use certain types of
candles and I'll give you you know what
kinds of candles if you like candles
what you should do and then no air
fresheners folks because of the VC's all
of these chemicals you're exposed to
benzines tulines Etc berm
Malahide so this is interesting incense
this was a study looking at incense and
the impact on cardiovascular mortal
mortality in Chinese people and what
they found was long-term exposure to
incense burning in the home environment
was associated with an increased risk of
cardiovascular mortality and the reason
why is because the chemicals that are
inside incense
reduce endothelial nitric oxide
production which is never a good thing
for cardiovascular health it also
affects metabolic Health affecting
lipids
increasing decrease in
cardioprotective HDL and elevating LDL
cholesterol and so this is why it
increases the risk for cardiovascular
mortality and there's some other
mechanisms that have been studied in
humans of the effects of the chemicals
that are found in incense on
cardiovascular function
this is showing just the various
systems that are affected when a person
uses incense and it's not just
cardiovascular that was just one study
like I said I can't give you everything
because it's just too much but it does
affect the respiratory system this is
why we're seeing increased incidence of
lung cancer in nonsmokers okay we're
also seeing increase in dialysis centers
around the country because of these
these chemicals that people are being
exposed to and inant have many chemical
and they have known renal
toxicity what do you want to do air
freshener synthetic air fresheners or
candles you want to um consider you know
natural essential oils these are
examples there's ceramic essential oil
diffuser there's this is a natural
candle and I'm going to go into a little
bit of what the candles if people are
interested
so when you're using a candle you want
to trim the wick a/4 inch to 1 188
before use and that helps it burn evenly
and it reduces how much of the s that is
created you want to avoid thade or
petroleum based candles if you a person
who likes candles because candles are
nice you want to make sure that the is
Fator petroleum
based absent it doesn't have any of that
avoid burning a candle for longer than
three hours or longer than the
recommended time when you get a candle
normally the manufacturer will tell you
how long to use it for and this is so
that you can reduce the amount of so and
indoor
pollution look for candles that are 100%
natural waxes so coconut soy or Beeswax
is what you want to look for and
fragrance you want 100% essential oils
you want to make sure if you're not sure
just you know contact the company and
ask them what the fragrance is but it
should be 100% essential oils the Wix
100% cotton paper hemp or wood okay and
that's going to help reduce your
exposure to
vlc's and any other types of you know
chemicals that are coming out off the
candle essential oil diffuser that's
fantastic if you're trying to create a
nice Aroma in your home because we all
like nice Aromas use an essential air
diffuser you can also simmer a pot of
water with cinnamon any herbs you like
cinnamon sticks orange pills cloves Al
vanilla make your own create your own
Aroma and and then make a homemade
essential oil airspray and that can help
you know give you the scent that you're
looking for your home without it being
so
toxic okay so this is the last slide I
do remember this so just to reduce your
overall exposure to your living room
space adopt a no shoe indoors policy
so you they found all kinds of bacteria
that's found in
hospitals in people's on people's shoes
okay they're coming home they're walking
in their home they're tracking bacteria
found in hospitals in their home and
also I think it was a study it was from
the University of Arizona and I think
they found aund no
421,000 units of bacteria at the bottom
of a shoe the sole of a shoe so you
getting all of that bacteria as you're
you know coming in to your home and not
to mention the pesticides and
insecticides because you're at the park
or you're walking somewhere where
they've sprayed you're tracking all that
stuff indoors so adopt a no shoe Endor
policy and if you yeah so they have to
also practice that and be okay with
taking your shoes off so you want to
vacuum and or wet dust often your home
so people dust they might dust but
that's not really doing anything that's
just uh displacing the the dust
particles that's all that's doing so you
need to use a wet duster that's actually
has a little bit of dampness so that it
can pick up more because dry dusting is
just spr spring it out that's all it's
doing and the vacuum cleaner you want to
have a HEPA filter with that vacuum
cleaner your
furniture you can go back and check this
but you want furniture that does not
have any flame retardants and
so there you can look underneath your
furniture and there's a there are tags
and if your tag says TB
B17 that's an absolute no that means
your furniture has flame retardance and
there's just so much in terms of health
hazards associated with flame retardance
that's a whole another
conversation and they made revisions
throughout the years and so you might
see a tag that says TB
117-2013
this just means that the furniture might
have some flame
so maybe there's one part of it that
does doesn't have it and another part
that does you have to check with the
company but this one you know you just
be cautious and then the tag SP 1019 is
for sure does not have any flame
retardant